

# **ABOUT ME**

I am a Computer Vision and AI enthusiast with a desire to become a top researcher and apply my knowledge in real world. There is no limit and with each day there is something new to learn. So I try to stay updated with the state of the art techniques and algorithms. I am an expert Python programmer. I work profesionally as a Computer Vision and Python developer. I have strong knowledge about Tensorflow framework of Deep Learning. I am also efficient in Java, SQL, Matlab, Octave, HTML, CSS programming languages. Even though my main focus of research is Computer Vision and Al related, I have also done basic research on Biometric systems, Information Visualization, HCI, Human Interaction with Autonomous Vehicles, NLP. I believe it's important to have all-round tech knowledge to keep up with the pace of modern

#### **BASIC SKILLS**

- Fast Learner
- Communication
- Leadership ability
- Team worker
- Determined
- Responsible

#### **LANGUAGES**

- English
- Bangla
- French

#### CONTACT



+801680734894



iqbal.hossain3273@gmail.com



https://www.linkedin.com/in/iqbal-hossain-14b91a194/



Dhaka, Bangladesh



https://github.com/lqbal0007

# **EDUCATION**

2015 - 2019

BSc in Computer Science and Engineering
BRAC University, Dhaka, Bangladesh, Website - www.bracu.ac.bd
CGPA - 3.54/4

2013 - 2014

Higher Secondary Certificate (Science)
Dhaka Residential Model College, Dhaka, Bangladesh
GPA - 5.00/5

2011 - 2012

Secondary School Certificate (Science)
Dhaka Residential Model College, Dhaka, Bangladesh
GPA - 5.00/5

# **EXPERTISE**

### PROGRAMMING LANGUAGE

Python



Java



Matlab



Octave



• HTML



• CSS



• PHP



• SQL



### PROGRAMMING LIBRARIES, FRAMEWORKS & TOOLS

- OpenCV Matplotlib Seaborn Numpy SciPy Pandas
- Scikit Learn Tensorflow CUDA Bootstrap OpenGL
- Tesseract
   CNN
   YOLO
   JSON
   XML
   VGG
   LabelImg
- HelmetJS
   PIL
   RNN
   Git
   D3
   GAN

## **RESEARCH AREAS**

- Computer Vision
   Image Processing
   AI
- Machine Learning
   Deep Learning
   Object Detection
- Motion Segmentation
   ◆ Pattern Recognition
   ◆ HCI
- Information Visualization
   Human Robot Interaction
   NLP

#### **WORK AND RESEARCH EXPERIENCE**

- Computer Vision Research in the Computer Vision and Intelligent System (CVIS) Research Lab, BRAC University (September 2021 Present)
- Undergraduate thesis on Computer Vision and Deep Learning
   Topic Identifying Bikers Without Helmets Using Deep Learning Models
- Artificial Intelligence course project Emotion Recognition using EEG signals
- Digital System Design (DSD) course project Smart Monitoring System For Elderly People Using Heartrate Monitor and Gyroscope for Emergency Response
- Computer Vision and Image Processing engineer at Upwork (Freelance projects) (2019 - Present)
- Data Visualization and Graphic Designer expert at Upwork (2017 Present)
- Python programming course creator and instructor on contractual basis for a professor of Cambrian College (Sudbury, Ontario) (September, 2021 - Present)
- Information Visualization project for the Director of Management, Cranfield University, UK

# **PUBLICATION AND RESEARCH PROJECTS**

#### **IEEE Publication -**

• "Identifying bikers without helmets using deep learning models" in 2021 International Conference on Digital Image Computing: Techniques and Applications (DICTA 2021)

#### **Research Projects -**

- Collaboration project with a PhD student, Concordia University on a Pattern Recognition project for identifying shop types from shop signs (both occluded and not occluded)
- Identifying house types using door fronts and their location for a tech startup based in UK
- Intelligent safety system for detecting safety equipment such as hand gloves, masks, surgical gowns, protective glasses to ensure complete safety in work places and medical environment
- Bangla Text Recognition using image processing techniques such as Gaussian Blur, Binary Threshold, Greyscale etc. and Optical Character Recognition system
- Audio to Speech convertion using AI

### **Ongoing Research Projects -**

- Object depth calculation from Motion Segmentation for better interaction with Autonomous Vehicles
- Image-to-Image, Text-to-Image translation, Photo Manipulation using GANs

# Summary of Honors, Scholarships and Awards

- Merit Based Scholarship in my undergraduate program for outstanding result (highest grade in all the subjects) in Secondary School Certificate (SSC) and Higher Secondary Certificate (HSC) exams and for maintaining a CGPA greater than 3.5 out of 4 in my undergraduate level. This scholarship allowed me to get 70% scholarship throughout my undergraduate level. Only 2-5% students approximately manage to get this scholarship as ticking all the requirements is really tough
- Dean's list based on semester GPA in 2 semesters
- BSc. in Computer Science and Engineering degree with distinction honour
- Golden A+ in Higher Secondary Certificate (HSC) for achieving the highest grade in all the subjects along with optional subjects. This comprises only 5-10% of total HSC students in a given year. The percentage varies year to year
- Golden A+ in Secondary School Certificate (SSC) for achieving the highest grade in all the subjects along with optional subjects
- Deép Learning Specialization cértification by Deeplearning.ai, Machine Learning certification by Stanford University, IBM Data Science Professional Certificate by IBM through Coursera, an online course provider
- Distinction certificate for taking the English exam International Assessments for schools for the class 8 students sponsored by University of New South Wales and being in the Top 4% in the region. This certificate would allow me to get a 20% scholarship if I choose to study in the University of New South Wales
- Top Rated freelancer at Upwork. Top Rated status is the highest honour at Upwork and it comprises only 10% of the total freelancers all over the world. I work as a Computer vision scientist and also as a graphic designer at Upwork
- Verified by Upwork for being a top freelancer and having a consistent outstanding reputation
- Verified Python Programmer by HackerRank and also earned the Gold badge
- Multiple awards in co-curricular and sports activities throughout my educational period